<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A declaration to Great Britain and Ireland, shewing the downfall of their princes, and wherefore it is come upon them: because Christ is riding on his white horse, conquering his enemies till he have destroyed Antichrist, who hath made the nations drunk with the cup of her fornications: and till he have destroyed Mahomet, that great deceiver of the people. / Written and directed to Great Britain, and all other nations; by me Robert Wharton, wel-wisher to my countrymen, and to all the faithfull in Christ Jesus throughout the world. With an humble advice to the Army. This treatise is approved and commended, and thought worthy to be printed, by Master Hugh Peters.</title>
            <author>Wharton, Robert, fl. 1649.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 55 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96291</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W1575</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E555_35</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R204066</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863775</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863775</idno>
            <idno type="VID">115989</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96291)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115989)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 86:E555[35])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A declaration to Great Britain and Ireland, shewing the downfall of their princes, and wherefore it is come upon them: because Christ is riding on his white horse, conquering his enemies till he have destroyed Antichrist, who hath made the nations drunk with the cup of her fornications: and till he have destroyed Mahomet, that great deceiver of the people. / Written and directed to Great Britain, and all other nations; by me Robert Wharton, wel-wisher to my countrymen, and to all the faithfull in Christ Jesus throughout the world. With an humble advice to the Army. This treatise is approved and commended, and thought worthy to be printed, by Master Hugh Peters.</title>
                  <author>Wharton, Robert, fl. 1649.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 15, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R.L.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1649.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "May 21".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Prophecies --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:115989:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DECLARATION To Great <hi>Britain</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> ſhewing the downfall of their <hi>Princes,</hi> and wherefore it is come upon them: Becauſe <hi>CHRIST</hi> is riding on his white horſe, conquering his Enemies till he have deſtroyed <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> who hath made the Nations drunk with the Cup of her fornications: and till he have deſtroyed <hi>Mahomet,</hi> that great deceiver of the people.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>REVEL. 6.2.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>And I ſaw, and behold, a white horſe, and he that ſate on him had a bow, and a crown was given unto him, and he went forth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quering, and to overcome.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Written and directed to <hi>Great Britain,</hi> and all other Nations; By me <hi>Robert Wharton,</hi> wel-wiſher to my Countrymen, and to all the faithfull in Chriſt Jeſus throughout the World. With an humble advice to the <hi>Army.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="license">
                  <body>
                     <p>
                        <hi>This Treatiſe is approved and commended, and thought worthy to be Printed,</hi>
                     </p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>by Maſter</hi> Hugh Peters.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>R. L.</hi> 1649.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:115989:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:115989:2"/>
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>blazon or coat of arms representing the royal emblems of England (a rose), Scotland (a thistle), France (a fleur-de-lis), and Ireland (a harp), each crowned</figDesc>
               </figure> TO THE READER:</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hy ſhould it ſeem ſtrange to any that the Lord Chriſt is going forth like a mighty Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, to overcome his Enemies, and to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn thoſe that ſtand in his way. I pray conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der how much the Church of Chriſt hath been in the Wilderneſs of the World, like the Ark upon the Floud, when the World was drowned, and for ſixteen hundred yeers hath that great Dragon caſt out a floud of perſecutions to devoure her by his wicked inſtruments, whom he hath ſet at work, yet hath the Lord mightily preſerved it in all ages to this time, and now the Lord is bringing her forth of her affliction, and to make her a praiſe upon earth: now are her enemies mad, deſpiſing her, and ſeeking to turn her back again, but their ſurviving will be to their own deſtruction: conſider, how have all thoſe ſped that have ſtrove againſt
<pb facs="tcp:115989:3"/>her, or but lent an hand againſt her ſince Queen <hi>Maries</hi> days, both Kings, Princes, and the meaner ſort of people and how have they been croſt in all their deſignes, and it hath been their confuſion which hath fulfilled the words of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Chriſt, <hi>Matth. 21.44. And whomſoever ſhall fall on this ſtone ſhall be broken to pieces, but on whomſoever it ſhall fall, it ſhall grind him to powder;</hi> ye, and he ſaith, <hi>he will bruize them with an iron rod, and break them in pieces like a potters veſſell,</hi> Pſal. <hi>2.9.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If this be his doing already in theſe latter years, then is it high time for us to conſider what we have to do, and to be ſeeking for the right way, not pleaſing our own fancies, but be like unto <hi>David,</hi> he ſaith, <hi>My ſoul is raviſhed with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, and never is at reſt, but ſeeks to know thy judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments high, and what may pleaſe thee beſt:</hi> ſo our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Ask and it ſhall be given you, ſeek and ye ſhall finde, knock and it ſhall be opened unto,</hi> ſaith our Saviour, <hi>every one that asketh receiveth, and he that ſecketh findeth, and to him that knocketh it ſhall be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened.</hi> I pray ſee what glorious promiſes we have to build upon, it is not upon a ſandy foundation, but upon that firme rock Chriſt himſelf who ſpake the words with his own mouth, who never caſt off any that came to him by faith, as Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> Heb. <hi>11. Without faith it is impoſſible to pleaſe God;</hi> For he that commeth to him muſt believe, that God is, and that he is a rewarder of all thoſe that ſeek him dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently. If it be ſo, let us be earneſt with the Lord, that he will be pleaſed to enlighten our ſouls with ſtrength from Heaven, as <hi>Paul</hi> was, who ſaid, <hi>Through Chriſt I can do all things, but without Chriſt he can do nothing,</hi> Philip. <hi>4.</hi> if it be ſo, that Chriſt muſt be our ſupporter while we live in this life, of our pilgrimage, and that all true holineſs muſt
<pb facs="tcp:115989:3"/>proceed from him, in who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dwels all the fulnes of the Godhead bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily, &amp; that without him we can neverattain to heaven, then let us ſeeke every moment of our lives for holineſſe in this life, and that will bring us to that haven of happineſſe which will make us happy to all Eternity, that never ſhall have end, which if otherwiſe our mindes be ſet to croſſe the Lords deſignes he hath in hand, and turn enemies to him and his friends that live the lives of holineſſe, be you ſure that your account at the laſt will be miſerable, as ſaith the Lord in the <hi>Proverbs, 1.24. Becauſe I have called and you have refuſed, I have ſtretched out my hand and no man re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded, but you have ſet all my Counſels at naught: therefore will I laugh at your deſtruction, and mock when the thing you feare commeth on you: Then ſhall you call, but I will not hear, they ſhall ſeeke me early, but ſhall not finde me, becauſe they hated knowledge, and did not chooſe the fear of the Lord:</hi> Then ſhall the Kings of the earth, with the mighty men, Captains, bond and free, hide themſelves in the dens; rocks, and holes of the earth, but all will not ſerve, for if they cannot hide them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from death, who is the Lords meſſenger, when the Lord comes himſelfe they ſhall not be able to hide themſelves from his fury, if this be ſo, that the Lords comming will be ſo terrible when he comes to revenge the cauſe of his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved, who hath been ſo long and many years in bondage and captivity, nothing but fury and revenge will ſerve his turn upon them that ſtand in his way, then let all thoſe who are of ſuch violent ſpirits be affraid and ſtand out no longer againſt this great work the Lord hath going on in the world; but let them become friends rather then enemies; <hi>Leaſt they be torne in pieces, and there be none to deliver,</hi> Pſal. <hi>50.22.</hi> Now let us conſider ſince the Lord hath begun to ſhew
<pb facs="tcp:115989:4"/>the power of his comming in <hi>England,</hi> ſince the laſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution in Queen <hi>Maries</hi> dayes, how have they ſped that lent a hand to Antichriſt? have they not been brought to the Block or to the Halter? ſo when the Biſhops with their wicked Counſell began to perſecute, how ſtrangely were they defeated in all their purpoſes? then the King and his No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, they would revenge the Biſhops cauſe and their own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes, and how ſtrongly were they overthrown, and loſt their lives? for as moſt know, their power was ſo ſtrong, that at euery field fight, the King had, he got the better at the beginning, but before the battel was ended, he loſt all; which did appear, he had power and ſtrength enough to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come all had his cauſe been good. <hi>But he being weighed in the Ballance and found too light, could not ſtand againſt the work the Lord Chriſt had in hand.</hi> Now, conſider, the Lora is not ſhaking and pulling down the great pillars of this Land onely, but he is ſhaking other Kingdoms as well, as doth appear in France and other Kingdoms, and thus will he doe among all Nations, till he hath taken poſſeſſion of all the Kingdoms of the World, that they may become the Kingdoms of the Lord and his Chriſt, as you have it in the <hi>Revelations.</hi> Now, when the Lord hath taken poſſeſſion of all, then ſhall that Propheſie be fulfilled which the Lord ſpake by the Prophet <hi>Eſay, And it ſhall come to paſſe in the latter days, that the Lords houſe ſhall be prepared in the height of the Mountains; and ſhall be higher then the higheſt,</hi> or, as may be ſaid, higher then the Kingdoms of the World, for his power, glory, and beauty: Then ſhall all Nations ſeeke unto him, a multitude of people ſhall ſpeak one to another, <hi>Come let us aſcend to the hill of the Lords houſe, he will inſtruct us in his wayes, and we will walke in his paths, for out of</hi> Sion <hi>ſhall come a
<pb facs="tcp:115989:4"/>Law and the Word from</hi> Jeruſalem, yea, <hi>and ſhall give ſentence among the Nations,</hi> yea, <hi>and the multitude of the people ſhall breake their Swords into Mattocks, and their ſpears into pruning hooks, they ſhall not learn War any more, nor lift up a weapon one againſt another, then ſhall the high heads of men be brought low, and the Lord only ſhall be exalted,</hi> Eſay <hi>2. Then ſhall be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled the word of the Lord concerning his people and his enemies,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Behold, my ſervants that rejoyce for very quietneſſe of heart, but ye ſhall cry for ſorrow of heart, and complain for vexation of Spirit: your name ſhall you leave for a curſe among my choſen, for the Lord ſhall ſlay you, &amp; call his ſervants by another name, Eſay 45.</hi> Now, to conſider, concerning this Propheſie, that <hi>Eſay</hi> ſpake of many things concerning Chriſts comming in the fleſh for the redemption of man, is accompliſhed, which was the greateſt worke of all works, but for the accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his power, in bringing his people from the bondage of their enemies is but now begun, and when he hath done concerning his enemies, and taken poſſeſsion of all Kingly powers and authority, then ſhall be brought to paſſe the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie of <hi>Eſay</hi> the Prophet, <hi>Shall learn War no more,</hi> which ſhall be fulfilled at the time the Lord hath appointed: now the Lord hath appeared for his people, and is going on his way conquering his enemies, either goe on with him, or goe out of his way of his fury, leſt you be found partakers with them in their ſinfulneſſe, and ſo be partakers with them of their puniſhment, then let us beware while it is called to day, leaſt if we come in the hardneſſe of our hearts, heaven be ſhut againſt us to all eternity, and then too late to call for mercie: therefore our Saviour Chriſt gives us warning,
<pb facs="tcp:115989:5"/>ſaying, <hi>Watch, for ye know not when the maſter com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, whether at noonday or at midnight, or at the cock crowing, or at the dawning; leſt he come ſuddenly, he finde you ſleeping: and what I ſay unto you, I ſay unto all. Watch:</hi> Mark <hi>13.35, 36.</hi> Now, I pray you in the feare of the Lord, conſider what the Lord hath done, and what he is now a doing, and the Lord enlighten your underſtanding that ye may ſee more and more of the Lords appearing for his people, and be partakers with them of their happineſs in Chriſt.</p>
            <p>The Lord unite the Nations together, that as we are but one people and language, ſo we may be of one heart and minde; which the Lord grant for Jeſus Chriſt his ſake. AMEN.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours <hi>R.W.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>To the Reader, l. 5. for much r. long, page 5. line 22. as for r. abhorr'd, p. 9.18. r. when ye, p. 10. l. 18. r. <hi>Eſſex</hi> from the Land ſervice, r. my Lord of from the Sea, p. 11. l. 18. r. appeare, <hi>ibid.</hi> l. 31. r. ſeem'd to frown on them. p. 12. l. 1. for take r. loſe, <hi>ibid.</hi> l. 33. r. buried.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:115989:5"/>
            <head>A Declaration to Great <hi>Britain.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O all my loving country men, whom I am bound to love, I am deſirous to impart a few lines concerning the great worke that God hath wrought for his Goſpel in this latter age of the World, eſpecially in <hi>England,</hi> where we are a Nation, as firſt, to conſider how he worketh, next what he hath brought to paſſe. It pleaſed the Lord in King <hi>Henries</hi> dayes about the 9th. year of his Reign, that the Lord brought to light the Goſpel here in <hi>England</hi> by the hand of <hi>Luther,</hi> who ſent it to this Nation, where it was accepted among many people with great joy and comfort to their poor ſouls: This being done, it pleaſed the Lord to continue it till Queen <hi>Maries</hi> days, then begun a great perſecution to come againe by that red Dragon which is ſpoken of <hi>Revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> Chap. 12. concerning <hi>Michael</hi> and his Angels who fought with the Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon and his Angels, which was figured out plainly by Queen <hi>Mary</hi> who gave the red Dragon for her Arms, and ſo plaid her part accordingly, as you all know by the ſtory, but it pleaſed the Lord to ſhorten her days and ſet up a Governour who favoured the Goſpel, then was the power of the Devil brought down, and whoſoever roſe up againſt the Goſpel were brought to the block or the halter: likewiſe the Spaniſh Navie who came to devoure up the Goſpel how were they overthrown in the ſea, and their great General <hi>Don Pedro</hi> brought in to the mercy of the Queen, after the Lord had removed her, he ſet up the King of Scots to rule over us, who before he came into <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> made a Covenant with his Miniſters to purge the Church of <hi>England,</hi> who came and was Crowned our King, which being done, and a Parliament called, then did the Devil, that red Dragon, begin to ſet his own ſervants, the Papiſts, to work, who thought when they had blown up the Parliament de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed a project to have proclaimed that the Puritans had done it, and ſo have raiſed the whole Countrey to out off the people of God moſt barbarouſly, but the Lord who neither ſlumbers nor ſleeps, befooles them all, and brought them miſerably to their ends, yet did not this great mercy put out King in minde how the Lord dealt lovingly with him in bringing him out of a poore Countrey into a glorious land, where he had all the pleaſures that might be afforded, as we all know, that he had delivered him and his Nobles from ſuch a deadly blow, and made him of a poor Scotch King a glorious Engliſh King, which would make me think the more the Lord had honoured him, the
<pb facs="tcp:115989:6"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:115989:6"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:115989:7"/>more he ſhould have ſought for to glorifie the Lord, but he did not, for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Covenant he made with his Miniſters in <hi>Scotland</hi> he neglected, caſting it behind his back, which when the Miniſters ſaw, they came into <hi>England</hi> to <hi>White</hi> Hall, where one of them made a Sermon before him, put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting him in minde how he had broke his Covenant with God and man, and how the Lord would lay to his charge his Covenant he made concerning purging the Church of <hi>England,</hi> he charg'd him deeply, but he charged him ſo deeply with it, that as ſoon as he had done his Sermon, he was ſoundly checkt for it, ſent to the Tower, where he lay a time, but means being wrought for him, he was releaſed, baniſhed the land, to come no more; but marke what befell, in ſhort time, the King married his daughter to the King of <hi>Bohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia,</hi> who were turned out of their Countrey, and have lived as ſtrangers in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other Countrey, and were maintained by the charge of <hi>England,</hi> and their children fighting againſt the people of God, as ye ſee to this day, when they were turned out of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> the next chance that befall, Prince <hi>Henry</hi> was poyſoned, thus were his children curb'd and cut off, though his children were thus miſerably brought under and cut off, yet did he not conſider nor call to minde wherefore the Lord had brought this judgement on his children, but ſinned yet more, by ſuffering a Papiſt houſe to be built up in <hi>Black-friers,</hi> but marke what befell, as ſoon as they were in their devotions with their ſtrange gods, the houſe fell down on their heads, as <hi>Dagon</hi> fell before the Arke of God, where were killed ſome foureſcore perſons, beſides what was maim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, yet did not this ſtrange work move him, but he ſinned yet more, ſending his ſonne to <hi>Spain,</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> to get a wife that ſerved ſtrange gods, and to make it appear more, procured a Chappel for Papiſtry to be built up at Saint <hi>Jameſes</hi> where it ſtandeth to this day; but take notice what befel him, he that was his deareſt friend, whom he preferred before God and his people, became his ruin, which was the Duke of <hi>Buckingham,</hi> who with his Mother wrought Sorceries, and ſo poyſoned the King as would have been proved if things had been brought to triall, thus was his end miſerable, who preferred the enemies of Jeſus Chriſt before the Lords worſhip, not ruling the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in obedience to the Lord: this being done, and his dayes ended, his ſon ſnatcht the Crown to his head, Reigning in ſtrange manner as ye have ſeen, not ruling the people as in obedience to God and the Lord Chriſt, but as a covetous King to God's diſhonour, preferring his own deſignes before Gods word; he ſuffering any thing to be done for money, preferring the friends to Papiſtry before Gods worſhip, and preferring the Duke that helped to deſtroy his father, before the whole Kingdome, ſlighting the whole Nation, and ſet him up in the throne of his heart; but miſerable was that wicked
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:115989:7"/>mans end, when he was cut off from him; then were the Biſhops and their friends ſet up in his heart, he allowing them to do whatſoever they pleaſed: then did they begin to make havock of Gods worſhip, changing the Sabboth into paſtimes, for people to ſerve the Devil; and ſet forth an Order for it: thinking that for ſports and pleaſure they could the eaſier draw the whole Nation to their deſigne, and ſo put down the true worſhip of God: then was Papiſtry advanced, and all the friends to it in high eſteem; then did they thinke all was their own, and nothing could hinder them, ſo jovially went they on: then went the King on in his deſignes, ſuffering all that could bring money into his Treaſury, to reigne as petty Kings under him, in pilling and pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the Nation by oppreſſion; as Patentees, and making a new Freedome; how many poore apple-women and broom-men, rag-merchants, and people of all ſorts, ſold and pawned their bedding, and their cloaths for a new Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; and when all was done, it proved a very cheat, thus was the Kings cof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers fill'd with oppreſſion: thus did the King, his Biſhops, and his wicked crue reigne for a time. But marke, what befel, when the Lord ſaw them thus triumphing in their jollity, like the unjuſt Steward, ſitting and drinking with the drunken, and ſmiting their fellow ſervants, <hi>Luk.</hi> 12. Then did the Lord begin to a wake his people, then did he ſtirre them up to prayer, then did they begin to multiply and flock together: then did the Lord put them. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.37. Thus ſaith, the Lord, <hi>I will yet for this be inquired of by the houſe of Iſarel, to do it for them: I will increaſe them with men like a flock.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But mark, when the wicked crue faw what was doing, and knew not what would become of their projects, then did they begin to ſmite them about the eares, impriſoning them, and baniſhing them; then did they ſee what they could do with <hi>Scotland,</hi> then were they thrown out with theſe white coats, then did the people in the City of <hi>London,</hi> begin to grow more ſenſible when they ſaw the Scots withſtand them, and ſo became ſtronger and ſtronger; when the King, the Biſhops, and their wicked crue ſaw their wicked deſignes begun to ſhake and cotter, then were they in a ſtraight, nothing would ſerve their turne but the deſtruction of the people of God: then did they in their wicked Counſels conjoyne with the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> to ſend an Army to cut off the City and take the ſpoile of it for his reward; then did they raiſe an Army againſt <hi>Scotland,</hi> cunningly carried the arms, and ſtrength from <hi>Suſſex</hi> and thoſe parts their joyning to the ſea, that the Spaniard might not be expoſed: thus, in their cunning deſignes did they conjoyn, but take notice how they were befooled, the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> ſending his Army hither, thinking all was his own, was befooled wonderfully; though he ſent ſuch great ſtrength, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving many friends to entertain them, as the Earle of <hi>Northampton,</hi> an arch
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:115989:8"/>Papiſt, and <hi>Pennington</hi> with his ſhips to aſſiſt him: <hi>Dover</hi> Caſtle that ſhould have been made ſtrong to oppoſe ſuch an enemy, had nothing to reſiſt them, thus did our home-bred enemies aſſiſt forreign enemies to cut us off, then did the Lord appear for us wonderfully, and provided a neighbour Nation to ſinke the Spaniards in the Sea, yet was it an impoſſible worke for <hi>Van Trump</hi> to have done, had not the Lord appear'd for us, for <hi>Fennington</hi> with his ſhips fired at the Dutch-men, and did them much hurt, for which they did ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe him when he went with the Queen into <hi>Holland</hi> to the <hi>Hague:</hi> how did the Lord work wonderfully in caſting our enemies into the Sea? who ſhould have cut our throats, and many of them that eſcaped with life came to the City to beg their bread, who ſaw the glory of the City, but could not ſhare of the wealth of it: now judge you whether the Lord appeared for his people or no; but ſee farther, how the King of <hi>Spain</hi> was ſerved after, he loſt his great Navy at Sea, next year after, he loſt the Kingdom of <hi>Portingale,</hi> ſo let all the wicked be ſerved, that joyne hand in hand to deſtroy the inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of the Lord.</p>
            <p>Now when the King with his wicked Counſell, could no way proſper, but his deſignes ſtill croſt, and befooled with going to <hi>Scotland,</hi> where he loſt his labour, and all the money that he had got in unjuſt wayes, ſpent in that deſigne for <hi>Scotland,</hi> then were the wicked crue enraged, but the more they ſtirred the more they enſnared: then began their woe: then marke how <hi>Strafford</hi> was ſerved for his wickedneſſe, then was the Biſhop taken by the Hornes like the Ram in the Buſh, and ſacrificed like as he would have ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the people of the Lord. Thus hath the Lord appeared for his peoole, yet for all this the enemies of the Lord will not ſee what the Lord is doing, but they will goe on, and though they ſee plainly that the Lord is deſtroying his enemies, yet will they be more vile, raiſing up War, but it proves their own deſtruction, as conſider the evill that our King hath brought on him and his poſterity, and all becauſe he could not ſet up Papiſtry, and bring the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion into a ſlaviſh condition, ô that wicked will that is in man by nature, though to the deſtruction of himſelfe and his poſterity, which though he had wealth enough by the revenues of three Kingdoms, yet would not all this ſerve him, but a tyrannicall government over the Nations, ſurely they that have hearts to conſider and well underſtand this, may very well know that he had no great love to the Nation, but to rule like a Tyrant, or a curſed ſtep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father, that loves the wealth the children are heirs unto, but ſtrives to make the children away: who would have gone from his people as he did, when he was ſo royally and lovingly entertained by them, a great gift given him, another to his Queen, and another to the Prince, by the Citizens of <hi>London,</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:115989:8"/>which was not the gift of one man but the gift of many: yea, how did the Citizens entertain the Queens Mother? thus did the people rejoyce to doe them good, and for all this kindneſſe, they ſought to ſpill our bloud: and who muſt he chooſe but Papiſts for his truſty friends, as <hi>Arundel, Lunſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> an arch Papiſt, to be Lieutenant of the Tower, to beat the City about our ears, this love and kindneſſe have we found at his hands for the great love we ſhewed him when he tooke up a War againſt the Scots, he ſpared their bloud, and granted their deſires, but when he came to reaſon with us, nothing but fire and ſword ſerved his turn, to deſtroy us a poore and blinde people, that ſhould ſo much deſire the life of him that was not only a deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the body but likewiſe of the ſoul, by ſeeking to put out the light of the Goſpel, and to have ſet up papiſtry, as you may ſee by his actions, under a colour, deſiring to have Religion as it was in Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> dayes, and ſo to have ſet up Papiſtry, but with his Lordly Biſhops, but all would not ſerve his turn, for when he had run his courſe, in the place where he had ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, in the ſame place he muſt end his dayes, a ſad condition, for in the time of his proſperity he built a Masking-houſe for the Devils worſhip, or ſporting, upon the ſame place where the Lords name was call'd on, the Masking-houſe being built up to over-top Gods place of worſhip, yet doe I not ſay that is the true place of Gods Worſhip, for the place that God chooſeth for his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip is in the heart, yet that place was choſen by man to call on the name of the Lord; therefore did the Lord, as for his wicked deſigne, and ſo brought bloud upon his head, as he hath done on his Nobles, and the reſt of his friends that were the enemies of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>But, me thinks, I heare him be wailing <hi>Straffords</hi> bloud, truly he needeth not, for never was man more ſorry for his friends death then he was for his, had he pittied this Nations bloud as he pittied his, there had been no War raiſed by him to cut off Engliſh men as he hath done.</p>
            <p>Some ſay that Duke <hi>Hambleton</hi> clears the King of <hi>Irelands</hi> bloud, as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Proteſtants there, how many times hath he been moved in every Treaty by the Parliament to cauſe War to ceaſe there? but would not yield to it, then judge you whether he be guilty of that bloud or no. Again, ſome ſay it was not lawfull for the Parliament aſſiſted by the Army to put him to death, will ye ſay ſo? are they not they whom the Lord hath put the Sword into their hands to execute vengeance on his Enemies? is his bloud dearer to him then the bloud of his Saints? though he was an utter enemy, ſo far as his power did reach, to cut off the people of the Lord.</p>
            <p>But you will ſay, that <hi>David</hi> would not lay his hand on his King, a great reaſon, for <hi>David</hi> knew that he was anointed to be King by the Prophet of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:115989:9"/>the Lord, therefore had it been preſumption againſt the Lord to ſnatch the Crown to his head, and not wait the Lords leaſure, for <hi>David</hi> was told by the Spirit of the Lord that he ſhould be King, and that <hi>Sauls</hi> dayes ſhould be ſhortned: Again, <hi>Saul</hi> was a freind to the Nation, cutting off the <hi>Gibonites,</hi> thinking to doe the people, his Subjects a pleaſure; but ye ſaw no ſuch af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection in our King towards the people his ſubjects, but take notice how the Lord dealt with <hi>Saul</hi> after he had deſtroyed him by his enemies, his wrath was not appeaſed ſo, but he revenged the bloud of ſtrangers on his ſeed, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed a dearth for foure years to come upon the Land, and would not be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſed till he had rooted out his poſterity: If the Lord dealt ſo with him that was a freind to the Nation, how much more will he be angry with thoſe that will ſpill the bloud of the Nation, and deſtroy the Lords Inheritance. Yet one great worke I doe behold, and I doubt a ſad one, that our Miniſters ſhould ſo much bewail his death that proclaimed them Traitors, who would not have ſpared their lives but have put them to death, and ſo have put out the light of the Goſpel, as you may take notice concerning his actions, and thoſe that were in counſell with him in their wicked practiſes: had it not beene death for any that ſhould have come to give him evill counſell againſt the Goſpel, or againſt the Lords inheritance: Had he been a godly Prince, would he have ſlighted the death of his Father as he did, when he was told he was poyſoned, and when a Parliament was called in the beginning of his Reign, how would he have ſearched out the offenders? but he cauſed the Parliament to be put by, and ſit no more: likewiſe, concerning <hi>Rochel</hi> work, what treachery was there laid againſt the poore Proteſtants there, judge ye, they ſent hither for help, againſt the Papiſts, for fear of being overcome by them; and he promiſed them help, but when their greateſt need and deſires came on them, he ſent the ſhips againſt them, whereby they were overthrown: thus from the beginning of his Reign to his laſt days hath he been an enemy to the people of the Lord; and will ye cauſe the people to mourn after him that ſo much hath ſought after their deſtruction: truely, a ſad caſe.</p>
            <p>Chriſt ſaith ye are my friends if ye do whatſoever I command you, I am ſure he doth not command you to mourn after his enemies, when he is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying them, do you not know that Chriſt is on his white horſe riding on his journey, conquering and overcoming his enemies, <hi>Revel.</hi> 6.2. And hath not he ſet you as watchmen upon the wals to give the people notice what he is a doing: is he not going forth to conquer the Kingdoms of the world, that they may become the Kingdoms of the Lord and his Chriſt?</p>
            <p>Then I pray conſider, what ye have to do, forget this darling of the world, and ſet not the people a mourning after him that ſpared not our bloud, but
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:115989:9"/>reach the people to mourne after him whom we have pierced with out ſins, even the Lord Jeſus Chriſt. But now let us conſider who are our friends concerning the great worke that is now in hand, begun in the World, are they not they whom you have ſtirred up in your Sermons to fight the Lords battell againſt the mighty? did you not take up that Text concerning <hi>Meroz?</hi> ſaying, <hi>Curſe ye Meroz, curſe ye bitterly the Inhabitants thereof, that come not out to helpe the Lord againſt the mighty:</hi> have ye not ſaid, let him that hath no ſword ſell his cloke and buy one? how have you been the cauſe partly of raiſing this Army, and how have they prevailed againſt your enemies even by your prayers? I pray remember the condition we were in many times, and how the Lord preſerved you and us by their hands, and how were dayes of thankſgiving ſtirr'd up by you to the Parliament, to cauſe the people to rejoyce with you? and ſhall all this be forgotten? I pray remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber <hi>Leiceſter</hi> worke, what a caſe were we in then, when the Countrey ſaid, What will become of the Round-heads now? how did you call us toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to faſting and prayers? and how were your Prayers heard by the Lord, and a gracious return from the Lord was ſent you by the hands of theſe men from <hi>Nasby,</hi> then how did we and you bleſſe the Lord for this great mercie ſo that ever after out enemies could never prevail, ſuch was the great mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of the Lord to you and us. I pray remember what you ſaid, ſome of you, when you ſaw theſe men give large and mercifull Propoſitions, when they had conquered your enemies at <hi>Oxford,</hi> did you not ſay, that they would prove pricks and thorns in their ſides and ours, and did it not ſo come to paſſe, as we have ſeen, and now they have overcome them again by the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty power of the Lord Chriſt, daſhing <hi>Babylons</hi> brats in pieces, ye goe about to hinder them, giving their enemies occaſion even to curſe them, as I have heard: ſure this is a ſad caſe, when ye ſhall ſeeke to weaken their hands, thus ſtrive not againſt them, for had not this been of the Lord, they had never done ſo much as they have: therefore count not them your enemies, for ye ſhall have cauſe to ſay once more, to call them your friends, when ye ſhall ſee plainly what the Lord is a doing.</p>
            <p>Who knoweth whether the Lord be going to make a new heaven and a new carth, or now as is promiſed, in <hi>Revel.</hi> 21.1. Know ye not that when a Noble man goeth to take poſſeſſion of a great place or houſe full of lumber that he will cauſe his ſervants to caſt out all the lumber that he may place his royall furniture in the roome, and will not a great Landlord throw out ſuch tenants out of his inheritance that will pay no rent, but abuſe ſuch tenants, that will pay honeſtly to their power: then I pray conſider what the Lord Chriſt is a doing, is he not coming to take poſſeſſion of his in heritance that he
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:115989:10"/>bought ſo dearly of his Father, and is not all the world his to do with all his pleaſure, wil he be tide to the ſpirits of men to do what they pleaſe, ſurely no; I pray remember how long the Church hath been in the Wilderneſſe of the world, and how the red Dragon hath caſt out flouds time after time to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voure her, and how he hath ſate like the great Prince of the World upon thrones uſurping authority over the Nations, and playing the tyrant over the Lords inheritance; and now he finds his time grow ſhort, and his Kingdoms ſhall be taken from him, he grows mad, but now is the time come that he muſt be caſt out one throne after another; that the Kingdoms of the World may become the Kingdoms of the Lord: and his Chriſt, <hi>Revel.</hi> 11.15.</p>
            <p>If this be ſo, that the Lord is coming as chiefe Generall, with his bow in his hand, ſhooting at his enemies, and with his Crown on his head, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quering the Kings of the earth, and the mighty men, trampling them and their crowns under his feet, that would not bow to his golden Scepter, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.9. <hi>Revel.</hi> 19.17, 18. If this be ſo, that the Lord hath begun already to take poſſeſſion as may appeare, by his doings here, as conſider what he hath done ever ſince the perſecution in Queen <hi>Maries</hi> days, how have they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpered that have had the mark of the beaſt in their forehead, or that have lent a hand againſt this work; that is going on in the world, how hath <hi>Spain</hi> ſped, for coming here? how hath <hi>Denmark</hi> ſped for ſending ſtrength hither to help the King againſt the Lords work; was he not almoſt beaten out of his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey by the Swedes? and what became of that Army that the Queen brought over hither all the Iriſh, French, and other Nations, came not they to their graves; and look on <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>France</hi> they muſt laſh on another while we were buſied here, what King would not help his brother King, rather then his Commons ſhould over come him? will be an example for other Nations to do the like, yet all this will not do: therefore, let us conſider what this power is, it is not the power of man, nor the ſword of <hi>Gideon;</hi> but the power and ſword of the Lord: as it hath appeared plainly, by many examples in this land: now if this be the Lords doings here. What will be his doings in other lands among the great and lofty Nations where he hath to do, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 27.23. Me thinks, I ſee them begin to ſhake, now is that red Dragon troubled, now are his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces muſtering together for the defence of his Babylonians among the Nations, but all will not do: for now hath the Lord been performing that promiſe that is ſpoken of in the 63 of <hi>Eſay, Now is he delivering his people, and now he hath begun, looke for no change, but to goe forward in the World, till he hath quite ſubdued that great enemy of the world, that hath ſo long tyrannized over the Lords inheritance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If it be ſo, that the Lord be ſummoning in the Emperours and Kings,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:115989:10"/>with their mighty men to appear before the Bar of his Juſtice: then is it time for us to looke about us; and be like the Virgins that have their lamps trimm'd, and their lights burning, that they may waite on their Maſter, the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25. who ſaith, <hi>Watch for ye know not when the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter cometh.</hi> If the Lord be on his way, deſtroying his enemies in his fury, <hi>leading them into captivity, that have led into captivities, killing them with the ſword, that have killed with the ſword, Revel.</hi> 13.10.</p>
            <p>Then is it time for the people of the Lord, yea, the Miniſters of Jeſus Chriſt to be united together, and ſeek to the Lord to have the Root of bitterneſſe that is among them plucked up by the roots, which hath been a great cauſe to Gods people to ſtagger and ſtumble in this time, when the Lord is exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting his enemies: Truly, it hath been a great cauſe of giving advantage to the enemy to laugh us to ſcorne; yea, it hath given them advantage to take up the ſword againe, which hath been the cauſe of much bloud-ſhed ſince <hi>Oxford</hi> giving up, and may be the cauſe of more, if not ſpeedily prevented by an agreement among Miniſters: who are divided, who knoweth whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Lord hath done with his enemies, will begin with his people, or no; and chaſtiſe them in the ſight of their enemies? &amp; will not this grieve you ſhall ſee the Lord laſhing you in the ſight of your enemies, for them to laugh at you? The Lord open your eyes that the errours which are between you may be plainly ſeen by you, ſo that they may be plucked up by the roots, and caſt into hell, from whence they came. Now the Lord bring you together in love, that your differences may be ſo ended, that the Lord may ſmell a ſweet ſavour in giving your ſelves up together in love to the Lord, ſo ſhall the people of the Lord greatly rejoyce, and your enemies be diſmiſſed of their prey they long and look for; thus will there be a great advantage unto a happy peace in the <hi>Nation</hi> then ſhall the glory of the Goſpell breake forth in this Land like a burning &amp; ſhining light to the whole world; which will be a great means to darken errours: then ſhall the Miniſters be ſeene once more like the Stars in Chriſts right hand, whom their enemies did once ſeeke to pull down by proclaiming them Traitors.</p>
            <p>Then will the Lord delight to do us good, and bring down the power of the enemie ſtill more and more, till he have quite overthrowne <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> and plucked down his throne, which ſhall be downe in his appointed time; which time is ſet, and known to the Lord, even to the very day and houre ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, which being done, <hi>Mahomet</hi> his time muſt ſuddenly follow then, then down muſt come all other thrones, where the red Dragon hath his power: and when all theſe Kingdomes of the world are ſubdued to the obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:115989:11"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:115989:11"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:115989:12"/>of Chriſt. <hi>Then ſhall the Dragon be quite conquered, and chained up for a thouſand years, Revel.</hi> 20.3. Then ſhall that Propheſie be come to paſſe, which was ſpoken by our Saviour Chriſt to his Diſciples, in <hi>Luke</hi> 21.24. concerning the deſtruction of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> where he ſaith, <hi>And they ſhall fall by the edge of the Sword, and ſhall be led away captive into all Nations:</hi> thus hath that appeared long ago, ſixteene hundred years; the next <hi>Jeruſalem muſt be trodden down of the Gentiles untill the time of the Gentiles ſhall be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled.</hi> Now according to the Propheſie of our Saviour Chriſt, <hi>When all the Kingdomes of the world are ſubdued to his obedience, then ſhall the Jews become an United Nation again, and Jeruſalem ſhall be builded a glorious City; the Lord Chriſt raigning ſpiritually among them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to conſider of the great mercy of the Lord, in bringing down the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of our home-bred enemies; what enemies had we in the Parliament to keep back the work, the Lord had going on for the defence of his people? how did they ſeeke wayes to overthrow all by treachery, by ſending money, and other proviſions in the time of my Lord of <hi>Eſſex?</hi> and ſo made our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies proud over us; had not the Lord curbed them, and kept them under; but when they could not prevaile, then did they take my Lord of <hi>Warwicke,</hi> and placed Committees in his roome, yet that would do them no good; they were ſo befooled by the mercy of the Lord; then to try another project, they choſe Sir <hi>Thomas,</hi> now Lord <hi>Fairfax</hi> to be Generall, and gave him a large Commiſſion, thinking it ſhould break his necke: now judge ye, how trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous they were to the Seats they ſate on, and to the City, yea, and to the deſtruction of the Lords Inheritance: O miſerable men! how did they lift themſelves up in their wicked wayes? as ye ſhall heare.</p>
            <p>After my Lord Generall had received ſuch a large Commiſſion from them, then did they give him nothing but preſt men, that ſwore they would run to the King and would not ſuffer a Drum to be beat up, to gaine ſouldiers in love to him, then did my Lord of <hi>Eſſex</hi> his men ſtand out by thouſands, being loth to forſake their old Generall, and ſerve a new Generall; then ſee further, their aſe practiſes: when the King was got out of <hi>Oxford</hi> to range abroad &amp; ſpoil, then was the Generall to beat againſt dead walls at <hi>Oxford,</hi> where he loſt his men, then in the mean while they cauſed the Leiutenant Generall and Colonell <hi>Vermuten</hi> who followed the King in the Reare to withdraw to their Quarters; ſo in the mean time the King fell on <hi>Leiceſter,</hi> where was loſt much bloud on both ſides, and the City taken by the enemy: thus may you ſee what treacherous Parliament men did hatch, for the uphol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding their Covenant they made to the Lord, and ſought to deſtroy all the work
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:115989:12"/>the Lord ſet them to do: ô wicked covetous men, what falls both to God and man ſeeking after nothing but covetouſneſſe and treachery; now are ye abhorred both of the Lord and men; a hiſſing to all Nations: now are your ſervants become your maſters; yea, and without a great returne unto the Lord, and great ſatisfaction to the Nation whom ye have deceived; ye are but miſcrable. <hi>Leiceſter's</hi> bloud cries out againſt you for revenge: the Lord lay it to your hearts that are guilty of it, that it may not be laid to your charge at the great Day, when the Lord Chriſt ſhall come to judge the World.</p>
            <p>But to conſider, the ſad condition we were brought into by their evill ways, I cannot forget: how did the Royall Party cry out all was their own? and what will become of the Round-heads? now truely, that time ought not to be forgotten: then how did the people of the Lord ſlock together, both night and day? and how did they prevaile with the Lord, even when we were at the loweſt? then was helpe and deliverance moſt precious then did the Lord ariſe like one out of a ſleep, rowzed up the ſpirits that were halfe dead, then were out enemies ſmote on the hinder parts; then was there no treacherous <hi>Hotham</hi> to be found, then were out enemies utterly routed; ſo did the Lord graciouſly for us, till our enemies were vanquiſhed: thus did the Lord croſſe the deſignes of wicked men, and broke their bands aſunder, mightily pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpering his owne worke: yet for all they ſee ſuch mighty overthrowes given to out enemies, yet would they go on plotting their evill deſignes; but when our parts got the better, then would they give way; patience by force: thus did they linger out the time, thinking all would turne, but the Lord laughs them to ſcorne, making them the out-caſt of men.</p>
            <p>Yet one thing is to be noted, after the Armies had conquered their enemies, giving them large Propoſitions, that they ſhould ariſe no more in oppoſition, they broke their Articles, and roſe againe, as did appear in <hi>Kent, Wales,</hi> and <hi>Eſſex,</hi> and other places: then how did they brag and vapour, when the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my was parted and engaged, and indeed put to ſuch hard ſervice, that the Heavens ſeemed to frowne on them; yea, and the whole World cauſed them to frowne, with many that before had taken their parts, which made their condition to ſeem very ſad: then did the Lord ſeem once more to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear for them, and gave them power over their enemies, then were they ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly reuted in every place where they were gathered together, then did the <hi>Scots</hi> invade the Land, thinking to overcome all, and ſo become maſters over us; who came not to ſight for the King onely, but to enſlave the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as did appear: if this be ſo, then what mad ſpirits have we, that would
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:115989:13"/>rather take all, and become Slaves to another Nation, then to be croſt of our fooliſh wills: the Lord charge our mad ſpirits, that we may ſee what is for our good, unite us together againe, and make us a happy Nation, that we may ſerve him; who ſaid, <hi>Firſt, ſeeke the Kingdome of Heaven, and all theſe things ſhall be added unto you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to looke further, how many opportunities had our enemies and leſt all friends? friends in the Parliament, friends in the whole Nation, except a few, that the Lord had choſen for us friends amongſt all Nations; yea even the whole World, except a few, the Lord had choſen, and the weaker ſort, to which maketh me call to winde a Speech, that the <hi>Dutch</hi> Embaſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour ſaid, when he had ſeen the Kings Army at <hi>Oxford</hi> and our Army that attended their motion, ſaid he, the King hath a gallant Army; but you have a good God to ſight for you: which was as much as if he had ſaid, If ye have not the Lord to fight for you, ye are undone: then judge ye, after all theſe examples, and great deliverances, whether the Lord hath fought for us, or no?</p>
            <p>Yet one great worke I muſt not forget, concerning the Leiutenant Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, and his Brigade. 2 Remember when the <hi>Scots</hi> came firſt into <hi>England,</hi> to oppoſe the King about Religion, out Parliament for their aſſiſtance in that worke, ſent them a great Summe of money, and ſo to depart the Land: which when the <hi>French</hi> heard of it, they made a play of <hi>Engliſh</hi> men, and <hi>Scotch</hi> men; the <hi>Engliſh man</hi> was ſtript naked from the ſhoulders to the Waſte, and the <hi>Scotch man</hi> beating him where he pleaſed; this being done, Low were <hi>Engliſh men</hi> laught to ſcorne? as the <hi>Scotch men</hi> could laugh at tis at their pleaſute: which was the greateſt blot that ever <hi>Engliſh men</hi> had put on them: but take notice how this blot was wiped off: the <hi>Scots</hi> with a great Army marched into the Land, thinking to be maſters of all, as did appear by their actions, but their cauſe being unjuſt, the Lord ſtrengthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the hands of our ſouldiers to ſight againſt them, who very valiantly ſcattered them like a myſt; marched into their Countrey, had their Demands, cauſed their enemies to be disbanded, entertained in their chiefe City with great reſpect: came off with honour to our Nation: and ſhall we be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfull unto the Lord for ſuch mercies as theſe be deſiring to have them? ſhall we be ungratefull to our friends that have wiped off ſuch a ſtaine from the Nation, with the ventring their lives? the Lord forbid, this great evill that reignes in their ſpirits; that ever we ſhould turne againſt our friends, that have ſpilt their bloud toſave us from being deſtroyed; the <hi>Lord</hi> hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble both Miniſters and people, that we may ſee our owne miſery, and amend,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:115989:13"/>that the <hi>Lord</hi> may be pleaſed to unite the Nations, that we may become the Temples for the <hi>Lord Chriſt</hi> to dwellin: then ſhall holineſſe be our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, and <hi>the Lord will delight to do us good:</hi> ſo ſhall we dwell ſafely, and none ſhall make us afraid; but for my part, that have wrote this Book, I have deſired that my hand might be dried up like the hand of <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> never to pluck it in again, and my tongue cleave to the roofe of my mouth, then that I ſhould write any thing againſt the Honour of Chriſt, I never took the like worke in hand before now, but all my prayer is, that the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions may be united againe, and that the <hi>Lord Chriſt</hi> may reigne over us. The <hi>Lord</hi> give us ſuch a Parliament as may hate covetouſneſſe, that they may doe that which is juſt for the poore Commonalty, that above all they may ſeeke unto the <hi>Lord,</hi> to know what is his will concerning a true Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, for his Worſhip: and this being done, ſurely, <hi>the Lord will delight todwell among us:</hi> which will be the happieſt condition, that ever Nation lived in; which that it may be ſo, the <hi>Lord</hi> ſtrengthen us with his holy Spirit to go on in a loving way, both Miniſters and people: and ſo the <hi>Lord</hi> proſper us all, while we are ſo ſeeking, and doing his Will; to whom be aſcribed all <hi>Glory</hi> and <hi>Honour,</hi> both now and evermore, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I pray marke well, and conſider what Inſtructions we have in <hi>Pſalm</hi> 146. ſo likewiſe in <hi>Iſat.</hi> 58.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:115989:14"/>
            <head>To the Worthies of the <hi>ARMY.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>BUt unto you the Noble Champions of <hi>England,</hi> whom the <hi>Lord</hi> hath rade Conquer ours over his enemies; conquering thoſe that were like the mighty <hi>Anakims</hi> of the Land, whoſe command was obeyed through three Kingdoms, and whoſe name was honoured upon the great <hi>Ocean,</hi> how hath the Lord made you like <hi>Joſuah,</hi> and <hi>Caleb?</hi> conquering the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the <hi>Lord Christ?</hi> and like <hi>David</hi> cut off the head of <hi>Goliah?</hi> and ſhall not the <hi>Lord</hi> be honoured by you for all this? ſurely, that were a great diſhonour to the mighty worke he hath put into your hands to do: I pray conſider how the <hi>Lord</hi> hath given all the Land unto your hands to diſpoſe of, ſcattering your enemies, and making them amazed: now doth all Nations ſtand and waite to ſee what will be the intent of your actions: ſome ſay, that ye are hypocrites, making a ſtirrup of Religion, to yet up into the ſaddle, and ſion thence, to the Throne; ſome ſay, that now ye are become Maſters of all, ye will become mighty men over your brethren; ſerving your own turnes, and to the poor Commons whom ye have fought for, ſhall be worſe enſlaved then ever; by having many Task-unſters reigning over us: Should it be ſo, your latter end would be worſe then your beginning, yea, and the <hi>Lord</hi> would ſerve you, as he did <hi>Jehn,</hi> who though he ſought the <hi>Lords Battles,</hi> and did all that was in the <hi>Lords</hi> heart for him to do, yet becauſe he did all for his owne ends, deceitfully; the <hi>Lord</hi> the camed to bring the bloud of the <hi>Lords</hi> enemies on the head of him and his poſterity: <hi>ſuch is the wages of them that do the work of the Lord deceitfully;</hi> but ye have not ſhewn your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>Lord</hi> gives <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> all who are the chieſe in the Army) hearts like <hi>John</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> who when he had done conquering the enemies of the <hi>Lord,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> which is a great work, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to be done <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> by great men, and Lawyers, for they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the poo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of their right; it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> they have perverted true juſtice and judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the poore, the <hi>Lord</hi> had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> them in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> their hands; and they had a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> how miſerably have they brake
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:115989:14"/>all? laying hold on covetouſneſſe and oppreſſion, unjuſtly robbing the poore Commonalty, though they had all their owne eſtates in their hands; the Kings Eſtate, the Biſhops Lands, Deliquents eſtates, and making Seſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merts on all mens eſtates: yet all this could not pay your Army, and can we looke for redreſte, juſtice and right, from ſuch Covenant-breakers as theſe? ſurely, no: the <hi>Lord</hi> will turne them out of their Anthority call them to account, as he did <hi>Achan;</hi> &amp; paid both them and their poſterity their wages, except a mighty change be wrought from above: if this be ſo, that the <hi>Lord</hi> will turne ſuch offenders out of his ſervice, that ſate on Thrones, as Gods, and thus chooſe you to do right and juſtice with the Sword; then the <hi>Lord</hi> give you hearts ſitting for ſuch a great worke, that the poor Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monalty may be relieved, and have their rights againe, which they have been wronged of: and thoſe cries that have aſcended up to the <hi>Lord;</hi> and that it may be your chiefeſt care to countenance the Goſpell, and be friends to all thoſe that have been partly the cauſe of your taking up the Sword: truly, the <hi>Lord</hi> hath made them inſtrumentall Shepherds to drive many of his Flocks to his Fold, though the <hi>Lord</hi> had determined before whom they ſhould be, &amp; now hath the <hi>Lord</hi> made a ſeparation among them, &amp; a myſt is caſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them, which maketh them faile in their judgments towards you, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the worke you have in hand; but ſurely, the <hi>Lord</hi> will drive away that great cloud, and cleare up their judgements towards you, that there may be unity and love between them and us: and that your actions which are to enſue, may beget ſuch love in the hearts of the people, that they may ſay ſurely, the <hi>Lord</hi> hath raiſed you for good to the Nation, which will be a greatmeans to draw the hearts of the Nation to joyne in the Worke of the <hi>Lord</hi> with you: and unite the hearts of the people that are divided: not onely to be in love one with another again, but likewiſe towards you: Now the <hi>Lord</hi> give you hearts, that ye have taken up the ſword to fight for the advancing of the Worſhip of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and the Libertie of the Subject, delivering the poor out of bondage, dealing to every man his due, and ſetting thoſe that are unjuſtly impriſoned, at liberty; which being done, the <hi>Lord</hi> proſper your proceedings, that ye may ſee the fruits of your labour with joy and comfort; And ſo I end, deſiting the <hi>Lord</hi> to direct your hearts to joyne with them that are not ſelf-ended: which is the prayers of many godly people for you, and ſo, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours to command (whiles ye go on in godlineſſe and truth) <hi>Robert Wharton.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:115989:15"/>
            <p>THE ſincere and genuine intent of the Author in this Treatiſe, being wholly to ſet forth Gods glory in his great Works done for this Nation, and to ſtir us up to be reconciled, and to live in love and peace one with another, and in righteouſneſs in our ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall places: ſhewing only the downfal of all Authorities that do oppoſe Chriſt Jeſus and his Kingdome, who will prevail: therefore I ſay: <hi>Imprimatur,</hi> 
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Theodore Jennings.</signed>
               <date>
                  <hi>April</hi> the 19th. 1649</date>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
